The word concussion evokes a fear these days more so than it ever has,
تثير كلمة ارتجاج المخ الخوف هذه الأيام أكثر من ذي قبل،
and I know this personally.
وأعرف هذا شخصياً.
I played 10 years of football,
مارست كرة القدم لعشر سنين،
was struck in the head thousands of times.
وتعرضت لآلاف الضربات على الرأس.
And I have to tell you, though, what was much worse than that
لذلك، يجب على أن أخبركم، ما كان أسوء من ذلك
was a pair of bike accidents I had where I suffered concussions,
حيث تعرضت لحادث دراجة على مرتين وعانيت من ارتجاج المخ،
and I'm still dealing with the effects of the most recent one
وما أزال أتعامل مع الآثار الناتجة من آخرها
today as I stand in front of you.
بينما أقف أمامكم في هذا اليوم.
There is a fear around concussion
هناك خوف يحيط بارتجاج المخ
that does have some evidence behind it.
والذي له ما يبرره.
There is information that a repeated history of concussion
توجد معلومات أن تاريخاً من التعرض المتكرر لارتجاج المخ
can lead to early dementia, such as Alzheimer's,
قد يقود إلى الخرف المبكر كالزهايمر،
and chronic traumatic encephalopathy.
والتلف الدماغي المزمن.
That was the subject of the Will Smith movie "Concussion."
كان ذلك هو موضوع فيلم (ويل سميث) "الارتجاج الدماغي."
And so everybody is caught up in football and what they see in the military,
ولذلك نجد الجميع محصورين في كرة القدم وما يرونه في الجيش،
but you may not know
ولكن قد لا تعرفون
that bike riding is the leading cause of concussion for kids,
أن قيادة الدراجة هي المسبب الأساسي لارتجاج المخ عند الأطفال،
sports-related concussion, that is.
وكذلك الارتجاج الدماغي المتعلق بممارسة الرياضة،
And so another thing that I should tell you
شيء آخر يجب علي إخباركم به
that you may not know
قد لا تعرفونه
is that the helmets that are worn in bicycling and football
وهو أن الخوذ التي يتم ارتداؤها عند ركوب الدراجات وكرة القدم
and many activities,
والعديد من النشاطات،
they're not designed or tested
ليست مصممة أو لم يتم اختبارها
for how well they can protect your children against concussion.
لأي درجة يمكنها أن تحمي أطفالكم من ارتجاج المخ.
They're in fact designed and tested
في الواقع هي مصممة وتم اختبارها
for their ability to protect against skull fracture.
لمقدرتها على حماية الجمجمة من الكسر.
And so I get this question all the time from parents,
ولذلك يسألني الآباء هذا السؤال دائماً،
and they ask me,
ويسألونني،
"Would you let your own child play football?"
"هل ستسمح لطفلك بلعب كرة القدم؟"
Or, "Should I let my child play soccer?"
أو، "هل يجب علي أن أسمح لطفلي بلعب كرة القدم الأمريكية؟"
And I think that as a field,
وأعتقد أنه من واقع تجربتي،
we're a long way from giving an answer with any kind of confidence there.
ما نزال بعيدين جداً عن إعطاء إجابة مؤكدة على هذا السؤال.
So I look at that question from a bit of a different lens,
لذلك، أنظر للسؤال من خلال وجهة نظر مختلفة بعض الشيء،
and I want to know, how can we prevent concussion?
وأود أن أعرف، كيف بوسعنا أن نحمي من ارتجاج المخ؟
Is that even possible?
هل ذلك ممكن من الأساس؟
And most experts think that it's not,
يعتقد أغلب الإختصاصيين أن ذلك غير ممكن،
but the work that we're doing in my lab
ولكن العمل الذي نقوم به في مخبري
is starting to reveal more of the details around concussion
بدأ يكشف الكثير من التفاصيل المتعلقة بارتجاج المخ
so that we can have a better understanding.
وبذلك يتسنى لنا فهم الأمر على نحو أفضل.
The reason we're able to prevent skull fracture with helmets
السبب في أننا قادرون على الوقاية من كسر الجمجمة باستخدام الخوذ
is because it's pretty simple. We know how it works.
هو بسبب أن الأمر بسيط جداً، لأننا نعرف كيف يحدث ذلك.
Concussion has been much more of a mystery.
لطالما كان ارتجاج المخ أمراً غامضاً للغاية.
So to give you a sense of what might be happening in a concussion,
لذا لإعطائكم لمحة عن ما قد يحدث في حالة ارتجاج المخ،
I want to show you the video here
أريد أن أعرض عليكم الفيديو التالي
that you see when you type into Google,
والذي تجدونه إذا ما كتبتم على (غوغل)،
"What is a concussion?"
"ما هو ارتجاج المخ؟"
The CDC website comes up,
يظهر لكم موقع الوقاية والسيطرة على الأمراض،
and this video essentially tells the whole story.
ويحكي هذا الفيديو كامل القصة على نحو أساسي.
What you see is the head moves forward,
ما ترونه هو أن الرأس يتحرك للأمام،
the brain lags behind,
يتخلف الدماغ،
then the brain catches up
ثم يلحق به الدماغ
and smashes into the skull.
ويتهشم مصطدماً بالجمجمة.
It rebounds off the skull
يرتد عن الجمجمة
and then proceeds to run into the other side of the skull.
ومن ثم يواصل حركته تجاه الجانب الآخر من الجمجمة.
And what you'll notice is highlighted in this video from the CDC,
ما ستلحظونه سلط الضوء عليه في هذا الفيديو من مركز الوقاية والسيطرة على الأمراض،
which I'll note was funded by the NFL,
الجدير بالذكر أن إتحاد كرة القدم الأمريكي هو من قام بتمويله،
is that the outer surface of the brain,
ذلك هو السطح الخارجي للدماغ،
where it was to have smashed into the skull,
حيث لا بد أنه تهشم عند اصطدامه بالجمجمة،
looks like it's been damaged or injured, so it's on the outer surface of the brain.
يبدو وكأنه تضرر أو أصيب، لذلك هو في السطح الخارجي للدماغ.
And what I'd like to do with this video
وهدفي من هذا الفيديو
is to tell you that there are some aspects that are probably right,
هو أن أخبركم أن هنالك بعض الجوانب الصحيحة على الأرجح،
indicative of what the scientists think happens with concussion,
في دلالة على ما يعتقد العلماء أنه يحدث في حالة الارتجاج الدماغي،
but there's probably more that's wrong with this video.
لكن ربما يوجد الكثير من الأشياء الخاطئة في هذا الفيديو.
So one thing that I do agree with, and I think most experts would,
لذلك أحد الأشياء التي أتفق معها، وأعتقد أن الكثير من الخبراء كذلك أيضاً،
is that the brain does have these dynamics.
هي أن الدماغ يمتلك هذه الدينامية.
It does lag behind the skull
حيث أنه يتخلف عن الجمجمة
and then catch up and move back and forth and oscillate.
من ثم يلحق بها ويتحرك ذهاباً وإياباً والتأرجح.
That we think is true.
الشيء الذي نعتقد أنه صحيح.
However, the amount of motion you see in the brain in this video
مع ذلك، فإن كمية الحركة التي ترونها في الدماغ في هذا الفيديو
is probably not right at all.
ربما ليست صحيحة على الإطلاق.
There's very little room in the cranial vault,
يوجد مجال صغير للغاية في الجزء الأسفل للجمجمة،
only a few millimeters,
فقط بضعة ملليمترات،
and it's filled entirely with cerebral spinal fluid,
وهو مملوء بالكامل بالسائل الشوكي الدماغي،
which acts as a protective layer.
والذي يعمل كطبقة واقية.
And so the brain as a whole probably moves very little inside the skull.
وبذلك ربما يتحرك الدماغ ككل قليلاً جداً داخل الجمجمة.
The other problem with this video
المشكلة الأخرى في هذا الفيديو
is that the brain is shown
هي أن الدماغ يظهر
as a kind of rigid whole as it moves around,
ككل جامد بينما يتحرك حولها،
and that's not true either.
وليس ذلك بالشيء الصحيح أيضاً.
Your brain is one of the softest substances in your body,
دماغك هو أحد أنعم المواد في جسمك،
and you can think of it kind of like jello.
ويمكنك تشبيهه بالجيلي.
So as your head is moving back and forth,
فبينما يتحرك رأسك جيئةً وذهاباً،
your brain is twisting and turning and contorting,
فإن دماغك يلتوي ويلتف وينثني،
and the tissue is getting stretched.
كما أن الأنسجة تتمدد.
And so most experts, I think, would agree
لذلك فإن أغلب الخبراء, كما أعتقد سيتفقون
that concussion is not likely to be something that's happening
على أنه ليس من المحتمل أن ارتجاج المخ شيئ يحدث
on this outer surface of the brain,
في سطح الدماغ الخارجي هذا،
but rather it's something that's much deeper
بل هو شيء أعمق من ذلك بكثير
towards the center of the brain.
تجاه مركز الدماغ.
Now, the way that we're approaching this problem
الآن، الطريقة التي نعالج بها هذه المشكلة
to try to understand the mechanisms of concussion
لمحاولة فهم آلية عمل الإرتجاج الدماغي
and to figure out if we can prevent it
ولمعرفة ما إذا كان بإمكاننا منعه
is we are using a device like this.
هي باستخدامنا لجهاز كهذا.
It's a mouthguard.
إنه واقي الفم.
It has sensors in it that are essentially the same
يحتوي بداخله على أجهزة استشعار تشبه أساساً
that are in your cell phone:
تلك في هاتفك النقال:
accelerometers, gyroscopes,
أجهزة قياس التسارع، وجيروسكوبات،
and when someone is struck in the head,
وعندما يتعرض أحد ما لصدمة في الرأس،
it can tell you how their head moved
تخبرك عن الكيفية التي تحرك بها رأسه
at a thousand samples per second.
في ألف عينة في الثانية الواحدة.
The principle behind the mouthguard is this:
الفكرة من وراء واقي الفم هي:
it fits onto your teeth.
أنه يلائم أسنانك تماماً.
Your teeth are one of the hardest substances in your body.
أسنانك هي واحدة من أصلب المواد في جسمك.
So it rigidly couples to your skull
لذلك فهي تقارن بصلابة جمجمتك
and gives you the most precise possible measurement
وتعطيك أدقّ قياس ممكن
of how the skull moves.
على كيفية حركة الجمجمة.
People have tried other approaches, with helmets.
جرّب الناس مقاربات أخرى، عن طريق استخدام الخوذ.
We've looked at other sensors that go on your skin,
ألقينا نظرة على أجهزة استشعار أخرى والتي يتم الصاقها بجلدك،
and they all simply move around too much,
وببساطة فهي كثيرة الحركة،
and so we found that this is the only reliable way
لذلك وجدنا أن هذه هي الطريقة الوحيدة الموثوقة
to take a good measurement.
للحصول على قياس جيد.
So now that we've got this device, we can go beyond studying cadavers,
لذلك الآن بامتلاكنا لهذا الجهاز، نستطيع الذهاب أبعد من دراسة الجثث،
because you can only learn so much about concussion
لأن الطريقة الوحيدة للتعرف أكثر على الارتجاج الدماغي
from studying a cadaver,
هي من خلال دراسة الجثث،
and we want to learn and study live humans.
ولكننا نريد إجراء دراساتنا على أشخاص أحياء.
So where can we find a group of willing volunteers
لذا أين يمكن أن نجد مجموعة من المتطوعين على استعداد
to go out and smash their heads into each other on a regular basis
للبدء بتهشيم رؤوسهم ببعضهم البعض على نحو منتظم
and sustain concussion?
وتحمل الارتجاج الدماغي؟
Well, I was one of them,
حسناً، كنت واحداً منهم،
and it's your local friendly Stanford football team.
وهو فريقكم لكرة القدم التابع لجامعة (ستانفورد).
So this is our laboratory,
إذاً هذا هو مختبرنا،
and I want to show you
وأريد أن أعرض عليكم
the first concussion we measured with this device.
أول ارتجاج دماغي قسناه عن طريق هذا الجهاز.
One of the things that I should point out is the device has this gyroscope in it,
أحد الأشياء التي يتوجب علي تبيانها أن الجهاز يحتوي على جيروسكوب بداخله،
and that allows you to measure the rotation of the head.
ويتيح لك ذلك إمكانية قياس دوران الرأس.
Most experts think that that's the critical factor
يعتقد معظم الخبراء أن ذلك هو العامل الحاسم
that might start to tell us what is happening in concussion.
والذي ربما سوف يخبرنا عن ما يصاحب الارتجاج الدماغي.
So please watch this video.
رجاءً شاهدوا هذا الفيديو.
Announcer: Cougars bring extra people late, but Luck has time,
المذيع: يتخطى (كوغرس) عدداً إضافياً من اللاعبين، ولكن (لاك) لديه وقت،
and Winslow is crushed.
ويتعرض (وينسلو) للإصطدام.
I hope he's all right.
أتمنى أن يكون بخير.
(Audience roars)
(يهدر الجمهور)
Top of your screen,
في الجزء العلوي من الشاشة،
you'll see him come on just this little post route,
سترونه يتقدم في هذا المسار،
get separation, safety.
ينفصل عنهم، بأمان.
Here it comes at you in real speed. You'll hear this.
في لقطة سريعة هنا. ستسمعون هذا.
The hit delivered by --
كانت الصدمة بسبب --
David Camarillo: Sorry, three times is probably a little excessive there.
دافيد كاماريللو: آسف، بما تكون ثلاث مرات زائدة عن الحد قليلاً.
But you get the idea.
ولكنكم فهمتم الفكرة.
So when you look at just the film here,
لذا عندما تنظرون إلى الفيلم هنا،
pretty much the only thing you can see is he got hit really hard and he was hurt.
إلى حد كبير، الشيء الوحيد الذي سترونه هو أنه تعرض لصدمة قوية وتأذى نتيجة لذلك.
But when we extract the data
ولكن عندما نستخلص البيانات
out of the mouthguard that he was wearing,
من واقي الفم الذي كان يرتديه،
we can see much more detail, much richer information.
نستطيع رؤية تفاصيل أكثر بكثير، ومعلومات أكثر غناً.
And one of the things that we noticed here
وأحد الأشياء التي لاحظناها هنا
is that he was struck in the lower left side of his face mask.
هي أنه تعرض للضربة في الجزء السفلي للجانب الأيسر لقناع وجهه.
And so that did something first that was a little counterintuitive.
وقد تسبب ذلك بدءاً في شيء غير متوقع بعض الشيء.
His head did not move to the right.
لم يتحرك رأسه لليمين.
In fact, it rotated first to the left.
في الواقع، لقد دار أولاً ناحية اليسار.
Then as the neck began to compress,
وعندما بدأت الرقبة بالضغط،
the force of the blow caused it to whip back to the right.
تسببت قوة الضربة في رجوعه ناحية اليمين.
So this left-right motion was sort of a whiplash-type phenomenon,
لذلك فإن هذه الحركة لليسار ثم اليمين تعد نوعاً ما كإصابة السوط،
and we think that is probably what led to the brain injury.
ونعتقد أن ذلك ربما هو سبب إصابة الدماغ.
Now, this device is only limited in such that it can measure the skull motion,
الآن، ينحصر نطاق عمل هذا الجهاز في هذه الحالات حيث يقيس حركة الجمجمة،
but what we really want to know is what's happening inside of the brain.
ولكن ما نريد معرفته فعلاً هو ما الذي يحدث داخل الدماغ.
So we collaborate with Svein Kleiven's group in Sweden.
من أجل ذلك تعاوننا مع مجموعة (ستيفين كليفين) في السويد.
They've developed a finite element model of the brain.
لقد قاموا بتطوير نموذج محدد من الدماغ.
And so this is a simulation
تعدّ هذه محاكاة
using the data from our mouthguard from the injury I just showed you,
تستخدم البيانات من واقي الفم للإصابة التي أريتكم لها،
and what you see is the brain --
وما ترونه هو الدماغ --
this is a cross-section right in the front
هذا مقطع عرضي للمقدمة
of the brain twisting and contorting as I mentioned.
يوضح إلتواء وإنثناء الدماغ كما ذكرت من قبل.
So you can see this doesn't look a lot like the CDC video.
تسنطيعون أن تروا هذا لا يشبه كثيراً فيديو المركز .
Now, the colors that you're looking at
الآن، الألوان التي تنظرون إليها
are how much the brain tissue is being stretched.
توضح إلى مدى تتمدد أنسجة الدماغ.
And so the red is 50 percent.
لذلك فالأحمر يمثل 50 بالمئة.
That means the brain has been stretched to 50 percent of its original length,
مما يعني أن الدماغ قد تمدد ل50 بالمئة من طوله الطبيعي،
the tissue in that particular area.
الأنسجة في تلك المنطقة المحددة.
And the main thing I want to draw your attention to is this red spot.
أما الشيء الرئيسي الذي أود لفت انتباهكم إليه فهو هذه البقعة الحمراء.
So the red spot is very close to the center of the brain,
البقعة الحمراء قريبة جداً من منتصف الدماغ،
and relatively speaking,
ونسبياً،
you don't see a lot of colors like that on the exterior surface
لا ترون الكثير من هكذا ألوان على السطح الخارجي
as the CDC video showed.
كما بيّن فيديو (مركز السيطرة على الأمراض).
Now, to explain a little more detail
الآن، حتى أفسّر تفاصيل أكثر
about how we think concussion might be happening,
عن اعتقادنا لكيفية حدوث الارتجاج الدماغي،
one thing I should mention
أحد الأشياء التي يجب علي ذكرها
is that we and others have observed that a concussion is more likely
هو أننا وأخرون لاحظنا أن احتمالية حدوث الارتجاج الدماغي أكبر
when you're struck and your head rotates in this direction.
عندما تتعرض لصدمة ويدور رأسك في هذا الإتجاه.
This is more common in sports like football,
يحدث هذا على نحو أكبر في رياضات مثل كرة القدم،
but this seems to be more dangerous. So what might be happening there?
ولكن هذا يبدو أكثر خطورة. إذاً ما الذي يحدث هناك؟
Well, one thing that you'll notice in the human brain
حسناً، أحد الأشياء التي ستلاحظها في الدماغ البشري
that is different than other animals
هي أنه مختلف عن أدمغة الحيوانات الأخرى
is we have these two very large lobes.
والسبب أن لدينا هذين الفصّين الكبيرين للغاية.
We have the right brain and the left brain.
لدينا دماغ أيمن وآخر أيسر.
And the key thing to notice in this figure here
والشيء الرئيسي الجدير بالملاحظة في هذا الشكل هنا
is that right down the center of the right brain and the left brain
هو أسفل منتصف الدماغ الأيمن والدماغ الأيسر
there's a large fissure that goes deep into the brain.
حيث توجد فجوة كبيرة عميقاً داخل الدماغ.
And in that fissure, what you can't see in this image,
وفي تلك الفجوة، ما لا تستطيعون رؤيته في هذه الصورة،
you'll have to trust me,
عليكم أن تثقوا بي،
there is a fibrous sheet of tissue.
توجد طبقة ليفية من الأنسجة.
It's called the falx,
والتي تسمى بالمنجل،
and it runs from the front of your head all the way to the back of your head,
وهي تبدأ من مقدمة الرأس على طول الطريق حتى مؤخرة الرأس،
and it's quite stiff.
وهي صلبة جداً.
And so what that allows for is when you're struck
وفائدة ذلك هو أنه عندما تتعرض لصدمة
and your head rotates in this left-right direction,
ويدور رأسك في اتجاه اليسار ثم اليمين،
forces can rapidly transmit right down to the center of your brain.
يمكن للضربات أن تنتقل بسرعة وصولاً إلى منتصف الدماغ.
Now, what's there at the bottom of this fissure?
الآن، ما الذي يوجد في قاع هذا التجويف؟
It's the wiring of your brain,
إنها الأسلاك الخاصة بالدماغ،
and in fact this red bundle here at the bottom of that fissure
وفي الواقع، هذه الحزمة الحمراء هنا في قاع الفجوة
is the single largest fiber bundle
هي حزمة الألياف الضخمة الوحيدة
that is the wiring that connects the right and left sides of your brain.
وهي الأسلاك التي تربط جانب الدماغ الأيمن بالجانب الأيسر.
It's called the corpus callosum.
والتي تسمى بالجسم الثفني.
And we think that this might be
ونعتقد أنها قد تكون
one of the most common mechanisms of concussion,
أحد آليات الارتجاج الدماغي الأكثر شيوعاً،
and as the forces move down, they strike the corpus callosum,
وبينما تتغلغل الضربات، فهي تضرب الجسم الثفني،
it causes a dissociation between your right and your left brain
مسببةً انفصاماً بين دماغك الأيمن والأيسر
and could explain some of the symptoms of concussion.
مما قد يفسر بعض أعراض الارتجاج الدماغي.
This finding is also consistent of what we've seen
نتيجة البحث هذه تتسق أيضاً مع ما رأيناه
in this brain disease that I mentioned, chronic traumatic encephalopathy.
في هذه العلة التي ذكرت أنها تصيب الدماغ، ألا وهي التلف الدماغي المزمن.
So this is an image of a middle-aged ex-professional football player,
هذه صورة للاعب كرة قدم محترف سابق في منتصف العمر،
and the thing that I want to point out is if you look at the corpus callosum,
والشيء الذي أود الإشارة إليه هو أنه إذا ما ألقيتم نظرة على الجسم الثفني،
and I'll page back here so you can see the size of a normal corpus callosum
وسأعود إلى الشريحة هنا حتى يتسنى لكم رؤية حجم الجسم الثفني الطبيعي
and the size of the person here who has chronic traumatic encephalopathy,
مقارنةً هنا بالشخص المصاب بالتلف الدماغي المزمن،
it is greatly atrophied.
فقد ضمر إلى حد كبير.
And the same goes for all of the space in the ventricles.
الشيء نفسه ينطبق على كامل المساحة بين البطينين.
These ventricles are much larger.
هذين البطينين أكبر بكثير.
And so all of this tissue near the center of the brain
نتيجةً لذلك تتعرض كل هذه الأنسجة قرب مركز الدماغ
has died off over time.
للتلف مع مرور الزمن.
So what we're learning is indeed consistent.
إذاً، ما نتعلمه متسق بحق.
Now, there is some good news here,
الآن، توجد بعض الأخبار الجيدة،
and I hope to give you a sense of hope by the end of this talk.
وأتمنى أن أعطيكم بارقة أمل بنهاية هذه المحادثة.
One of the things that we've noticed,
أحد الأشياء التي لاحظناها،
specifically about this mechanism of injury,
بالتحديد حول آلية عمل الإصابة هذه،
is although there's a rapid transmission of the forces down this fissure,
هي أنه على الرغم من وجود انتقال سريع للضربات أسفل هذا التجويف،
it still takes a defined amount of time.
إلا أنه ما يزال يتطلب قدراً محدداً من الزمن.
And what we think is that if we can slow the head down just enough
وما نفكر به هو, إذا ما استطعنا إبطاء حركة الرأس بالقدر الكافي
so that the brain does not lag behind the skull
الذي يمنع الدماغ من التخلف عن الجمجمة
but instead it moves in synchrony with the skull,
لذلك عوضاً من أن يتحرك في تزامن مع الجمجمة،
then we might be able to prevent this mechanism of concussion.
حينها قد نتمكن من منع آلية حركة الارتجاج الدماغي هذه.
So how can we slow the head down?
إذاً كيف لنا أن نبطء من سرعة الرأس؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A gigantic helmet.
خوذة عملاقة.
So with more space, you have more time,
إذاً بمساحة أكبر، تحصل على مزيد من الوقت،
and this is a bit of a joke, but some of you may have seen this.
هذه مجرد مزحة، ولكن ربما رأى البعض منكم ذلك.
This is bubble soccer, and it's a real sport.
هذه كرة الفقاعة وهي رياضة حقيقية.
In fact, I saw some young adults
في الواقع، رأيت بعض البالغين
playing this sport down the street from my house the other day,
منذ بضعة أيام وأنا في بيتي يلعبون هذه الرياضة في الشارع،
and as far as I know there have been no reported concussions.
وعلى حد علمي لم يتم التلبيغ عن أي حالات ارتجاج دماغي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But in all seriousness, this principle does work,
لكن بكل جدية، هذه المبدأ ناجح،
but this has gone too far.
ولكن هذا الأمر ذهب بعيداً.
This isn't something that's practical for bike riding or playing football.
ليس هذا شيئاً عملياً لقيادة دراجة أو لعب كرة قدم.
And so we are collaborating with a company in Sweden called Hövding.
لذلك نتعاون مع شركة في السويد تدعى (هوفدينغ).
Some of you may have seen their work,
ربما اتطلع البعض منكم على أعمالهم،
and they're using the same principle of air to give you some extra space
حيث يستخدمون نفس مبدأ الهواء لإعطاء المزيد من المساحة
to prevent concussion.
للوقاية من الارتجاج الدماغي.
Kids, don't try this at home please.
أيها الأطفال، رجاءً لا تجربوا هذا في المنزل.
This stuntman does not have a helmet.
لا يرتدي مؤدي الحركات هذا خوذة.
He instead has a neck collar,
بدلاً عن ذلك يرتدي طوق عنق،
and this neck collar has sensors in it,
ويحتوي طوق العنق هذا على أجهزة استشعار،
the same type of sensors that are in our mouthguard,
نفس أجهزة الاستشعار الموجودة في واقي الفم،
and it detects when he's likely to have a fall,
وتكشف عن احتمالية تعرضه للسقوط،
and there's an airbag that explodes and triggers,
كما توجد وسادة هوائية تنفتح وتنطلق،
the same way that an airbag works in your car, essentially.
بنفس الطريقة التي تعمل بها الوسادة الهوائية في سيارتك.
And in the experiments we've done in my lab with their device,
وفي التجارب التي أجريناها في مختبري بمساعدة أجهزتهم،
we found that it can greatly reduce the risk of concussion in some scenarios
وجد أن بإمكان ذلك التقليل إلى حد كبير من نسبة التعرض لارتجاج الدماغ في بعض الحالات
compared to a normal bicycle helmet.
بالمقارنة مع خوذة الدراجة الهوائية العادية.
So it's a pretty exciting development.
لذا يعد ذلك تطوراً مثيراً للغاية.
But in order for us to actually realize the benefits of technology
ولكن حتى ندرك فعلاً فوائد التقنية
that can prevent concussion,
التي من الممكن أن تقي من الارتجاج الدماغي،
it needs to meet regulations.
يتطلب الأمر أن تخضع لضوابط.
That's a reality.
ذلك هو الواقع.
And this device is for sale in Europe
وهذا الجهاز متاح للبيع في أوروبا
but is not for sale in the US, and probably won't be any time soon.
ولكنه وغير متاح في الولايات المتحدة، وربما لن يكون في وقت قريب.
So I wanted to tell you why.
لذا أودّ أن أخبركم بالسبب.
There are some good reasons and then there are some not so good reasons.
هناك بعض الأسباب الجيدة وأخرى ليست جيدة بالدرجة الكافية.
Bike helmets are federally regulated.
خوذ الدراجات مجازة إتحادياً.
The Consumer Product Safety Commission has been given jurisdiction
أعطيت لجنة سلامة المنتجات الإستهلاكية الإختصاص
to approve any bike helmet for sale,
للموافقة على بيع أي خوذة دراجة،
and this is the test they use.
وهذا هو الاختبار الذي يجرونه.
This is back to what I was telling you at the beginning about skull fracture.
لهذا علاقة بما كنت أقوله في البداية بخصوص كسر الجمجمة.
That's what this test is for.
ذلك هو الهدف من هذا الاختبار.
And that's an important thing to do.
وذاك شيء من الأهمية بمكان لفعله.
It can save your life, but it's not sufficient, I would say.
قد ينقذ ذلك حياتك، ولكن سأقول أن ذلك ليس كافياً،
So for example, one thing this test doesn't evaluate
لذلك على سبيل المثال، أحد الأشياء التي لا يقيّمها هذا الاختبار
is it doesn't tell you is that airbag going to trigger
هي أنه لا يوضح لك إذا ما كانت الوسادة الهوائية ستنطلق
at the right time and place, and not trigger when it doesn't need to?
في الوقت والمكان المناسبين، وأنها لن تنفتح حين عدم الحاجة إليها؟
Similarly, it's not going to tell you
بالمثل، فإنها لن توضح لكم
is this helmet likely to prevent concussion or not?
ما إذا كانت ستقي من الارتجاج الدماغي أم لا؟
And if you look at football helmets, which aren't regulated,
وإذا ما ألقيتم نظرة على خُوذ كرة القدم، الغير مجازة،
they still have a very similar test.
ما تزال يجرى عليها نفس الاختبار.
They're not regulated by the government, anyway.
لم تجزها الحكومة على أي حال.
They have an industry body, which is the way most industries work.
لديهم كيان صناعي، وهي الطريقة التي تعمل بها أغلب الصناعات.
But this industry body, I can tell you, has been quite resistant
ولكن يمكنني أن أخبركم أن هذا الكيان الصناعي، ظل معارضاً لدرجة كبيرة
to updating their standards.
لتحديث معاييره.
So in my lab, we are working on not only the mechanism of concussion,
لذلك لا نعمل في مختبري على آلية عمل الارتجاج الدماغي فقط،
but we want to understand how can we have better test standards?
ولكننا نود أن نفهم كيف لنا أن نحصل على معايير اختبار أفضل؟
And we hope that the government can use this type of information
ونتمى أن تستخدم الحكومة هذا النوع من المعلومات
to encourage innovation
لتشجيع الإبداع
by letting consumers know
عن طريق جعل المستهلكين يعرفون
how protected are you with a given helmet.
إلى أي درجة هم محميون بالخوذ المعطاة لهم.
And I want to bring this back finally to the original question I asked,
أودّ العودة مرة أخيرة للسؤال الأصلي الذي ألقيته،
which is, would I feel comfortable letting my child play football
وهو هل سأكون مطمئناً لترك ابني يلعب كرة القدم
or ride a bicycle?
أو يقود دراجة هوائية؟
And this might be just a result of my own traumatic experience.
وقد يكون هذا فقط نتيجة لتجربتي الصادمة.
I'm much more nervous about my daughter, Rose, riding a bicycle.
أِشعر بقلق كبير تجاه ابنتي (روز) وهي تركب دراجة.
So she's a year and a half old,
عمرها سنة ونصف،
and she's already, well, wants to anyway, race down the streets of San Francisco.
وهي تريد سلفاً، حسناً، كما يريد أي أحد، أن تتسابق في شوارع (سان فرانسسكو).
This is the bottom of one of these streets.
هنا في أحد هذه الشوارع.
And so my personal goal is to -- and I believe this is possible --
ولذلك فإن هدفي الشخصي هو -- وأنا أؤمن أن هذا ممكن --
is to further develop these technologies,
هو مزيد من التطوير لهذه التقنيات،
and in fact, we're working on something in my lab in particular
وفي الحقيقة، نعمل على شيء في مخبري على وجه الخصوص
that really makes optimal use of the given space of a helmet.
يحقق الاستخدام الأمثل للمساحة التي تتيحها الخوذة.
And I am confident that we will be able to,
وكلي ثقة أنه سيكون بمقدورنا،
before she's ready to ride a two-wheeler,
قبل أن تتمكن من قيادة دراجة بعجلتين،
have something available
أن نتيح شيئاً ما
that can in fact really reduce the risk of concussion
سيقلل فعلاً من خطر الارتجاج الدماغي
and comply with regulatory bodies.
ويتوافق مع الهيئات التنظيمية.
And so what I'd like to do --
لذلك ما أود فعله --
and I know that this is for some of you of more immediate nature,
وأعرف أن هذا للبعض منكم من ذوي الطبيعة التي لا تحتمل التأخير،
I've got a couple years here --
قضيت بضعة سنين هنا --
is to be able to tell parents and grandparents when I'm asked,
أن يكون بمقدوري أن أخبر الآباء والأجداد عندما يتم إلقاء الأسئلة علي،
it is safe and healthy for your children to engage in these activities.
أن من الآمن والصحي لأبنائكم أن ينخرطوا في هذه النشاطات.
And I'm very fortunate to have a wonderful team at Stanford
وأنا محظوظ للغاية كوني أعمل مع فريق رائع في جامعة (ستانفورد)
that's working hard on this.
والذي يعمل بجد على هذا الأمر.
So I hope to come back in a few years with the final story,
لذلك أتمنى أن أعود مجدداً خلال بضعة سنين بالقصة النهائية،
but for now I will tell you,
ولكن الآن سأقول لكم،
please don't just be afraid when you hear the word concussion.
رجاءً لا تشعروا بالخوف عند سماعكم لكلمة ارتجاج دماغي.
There is hope.
هناك أمل.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)